<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet href="/scripts/pretty-feed-v3.xsl" type="text/xsl"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:h="http://www.w3.org/TR/html4/"><channel><title>विचारमञ्जरी | Vichāramañjarī</title><description>Welcome to the Garden of Thoughts.</description><link>https://icaran.github.io</link><item><title>The Great Abdication of Indian Education</title><link>https://icaran.github.io/blog/abdication_1</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://icaran.github.io/blog/abdication_1</guid><description>Bachelors isn&apos;t even worth it anymore honestly for a lot of people.</description><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;import { Aside } from &apos;astro-pure/user&apos;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India&apos;s higher education system has become a parasitic institution that extracts money while providing minimal education. Engineering colleges can&apos;t teach, graduates lack real skills despite having degrees, and society has normalized this dysfunction. We&apos;ve created &quot;educated-yet-ignorant&quot; graduates who possess credentials but no competence, leading to massive resource waste and civilizational decline. The system survives through monopolistic control over degree distribution rather than educational quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We stand witness to one of the most devastating institutional failures of our time: the systematic transformation of India&apos;s higher educational system from engines of human capital development into elaborate theaters of credentialism. This phenomenon—what we term &lt;em&gt;educational parasitism&lt;/em&gt;—represents institutions that extract societal resources while providing minimal genuine value, surviving purely through monopolistic control over credentials that society has been conditioned to accept as meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;{/* &lt;img src=&quot;https://icaran.github.io/newBlog/_astro/cover.C9VzzxgY_Iy4Q5.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot;&gt; */}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. Defining Educational Parasitism: The Anatomy of Institutional Failure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Educational parasitism occurs when learning institutions maintain their social legitimacy and economic viability not through the quality of education they provide, but through their gatekeeping function in credentialization processes. Unlike biological parasites that weaken their hosts gradually, educational parasites create a more insidious form of damage: they manufacture what we might call &lt;em&gt;parha-likha-anparh&lt;/em&gt;—the educated-yet-ignorant graduate who possesses degrees but lacks genuine competence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This represents more than mere pedagogical incompetence; it signals a fundamental breakdown in the social contract between educational institutions and society. When ninety-nine percent of engineering colleges cannot effectively teach their core subjects, we witness not isolated failures but systemic collapse masquerading as educational expansion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. The Credentialization Trap: Manufacturing Human Capital Stagflation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The contemporary Indian higher education landscape exhibits characteristics remarkably similar to economic stagflation—credential inflation occurring simultaneously with competency stagnation. Students spend four years in engineering programs, companies hire these graduates for roles requiring no engineering knowledge, and society perpetuates this elaborate charade because each participant benefits from maintaining the fiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This dynamic creates what economists recognize as a classic coordination failure. Educational institutions profit from fee collection without delivering education, employers fill human resource requirements on paper while conducting extensive screening processes that effectively ignore formal credentials, and students receive degrees that function primarily as expensive signaling devices rather than indicators of actual capability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most troubling aspect lies in society&apos;s normalization of this dysfunction. We have collectively accepted that &lt;em&gt;&quot;college nahi parhayega&quot;&lt;/em&gt; (colleges won&apos;t teach)—an abdication that would be unthinkable in other sectors. We would never accept hospitals that don&apos;t heal, courts that don&apos;t deliver justice, or bridges that don&apos;t bear weight, yet we have embraced educational institutions that don&apos;t educate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;3. The Export-Import Syndrome: Protected Markets and Innovation Deficit&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indian educational institutions operate within what we might characterize as an import-substitution model of learning—they provide domestic alternatives to genuine education while remaining protected from international competition or meaningful quality assessment. Just as companies operating solely in protected domestic markets lack innovation incentives, our educational institutions face no external validation of their output quality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This creates profound information asymmetries. Parents and students cannot easily assess educational quality, while employers develop elaborate screening mechanisms precisely because they cannot trust the credentials the system produces. The result is massive resource misallocation—society invests heavily in educational infrastructure that produces negative value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider the research infrastructure in premier institutions, where expensive imported equipment sits in laboratories that function more as museums than centers of innovation. PhD students describe their research environments as decorative spaces designed for publication generation rather than genuine scientific inquiry. This represents the completion of a vicious cycle where form has completely divorced from function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;4. The Demographic Dividend Delusion: Staggered Unemployment as Policy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India&apos;s educational expansion strategy reflects what we term the &quot;demographic dividend fallacy&quot;—the belief that simply credentializing large numbers of people would automatically translate into economic growth. Instead, we have implemented a Chinese-style approach to unemployment management, keeping people in educational institutions longer to delay their entry into saturated job markets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This strategy creates what economists call &quot;staggered unemployment&quot;—a system where potential joblessness is temporarily hidden within extended educational timelines rather than being addressed through genuine skill development or job creation. The recent phenomenon of major corporations indefinitely delaying onboarding for hundreds of graduates perfectly illustrates this system&apos;s ultimate unsustainability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;5. The Missing Markets Problem: When Money Cannot Motivate&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This analysis reveals a fundamental challenge that extends beyond education into broader questions of social organization. Certain essential social functions—teaching, research, military service—may require motivational structures beyond simple financial incentives. Modern market economies assume that sufficient monetary rewards can attract talent to any necessary social function, but this assumption proves inadequate for roles requiring intrinsic motivation, social prestige, or long-term commitment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditional social structures once provided non-monetary incentives through guaranteed status, social recognition, and occupational pride. The breakdown of these structures without adequate market-based alternatives has created what economists recognize as &quot;missing markets&quot;—areas where necessary social functions lack effective coordination mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This analysis leads us to an uncomfortable but important recognition: some form of occupational specialization with social reinforcement may be economically necessary, even if we reject the oppressive aspects of historical caste systems. The challenge lies in creating such specialization through voluntary rather than hereditary mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;6. Global Competition and the Inevitability of Reckoning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;India&apos;s educational dysfunction occurs within an increasingly competitive global context. As other developing regions rapidly improve their educational systems and artificial intelligence automates routine tasks, our elaborate system of credential distribution faces inevitable obsolescence. The comparison with Sub-Saharan Africa proves particularly sobering—regions we once considered less developed are now implementing educational reforms that may soon surpass our capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This global competitive pressure creates what we might call &quot;civilizational stakes.&quot; A society that cannot effectively transmit knowledge and skills to its younger generation has placed its long-term survival at risk. We face the potential end of India&apos;s demographic dividend not because our population is aging, but because we systematically waste human potential through institutional failure.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><h:img src="/newBlog/_astro/cover.C9VzzxgY.jpeg"/><enclosure url="/newBlog/_astro/cover.C9VzzxgY.jpeg"/></item><item><title>Fixing India&apos;s Failing Institutions</title><link>https://icaran.github.io/blog/abdication_2</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://icaran.github.io/blog/abdication_2</guid><description>Bachelors isn&apos;t even worth it anymore honestly for a lot of people. But we need to fix this!</description><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 18:30:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;import { Aside } from &apos;astro-pure/user&apos;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A mandatory competency examinations system could fix India&apos;s education crisis: mandatory competency exams for all engineering graduates with small cash rewards for decent performance. Colleges whose students consistently fail would be shut down. This creates direct accountability between educational quality and institutional survival, forces colleges to actually teach, and eliminates thousands of worthless degree mills while concentrating resources on institutions that work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;{/* &lt;img src=&quot;https://icaran.github.io/newBlog/_astro/cover.P9-NIKh0_1GhHS0.webp&quot; alt=&quot;Image&quot;&gt; */}&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;1. A Promising Solution: The Universal Competency Assessment Model&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The path toward reform may lie in implementing a comprehensive accountability system through mandatory competency examinations—a &quot;GATE Lite&quot; approach that could fundamentally reshape the educational landscape. This solution deserves serious consideration as it addresses the core dysfunction while creating powerful incentives for genuine improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mechanism would work as follows: Every engineering graduate would be required to take a standardized competency examination covering fundamental engineering principles—essentially a simplified version of the existing GATE exam. Crucially, this wouldn&apos;t be a high-stakes entrance test but rather a baseline competency assessment that every graduate must attempt after completing their degree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&apos;s how this can be advantageous: Students would receive modest financial rewards based on their performance—perhaps 1,000-2,000 rupees for decent scores. This isn&apos;t life-changing money, but it&apos;s enough to ensure students won&apos;t simply boycott the exam or deliberately perform poorly. Since they&apos;ve already invested four years in their education and are sitting for the exam anyway, most would make a reasonable effort to score well for the small monetary incentive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real power lies in institutional accountability. Colleges whose graduates consistently perform poorly on these assessments would face closure. This creates a direct link between educational quality and institutional survival—something completely absent in the current system. Suddenly, colleges would have powerful incentives to actually teach rather than merely process students through degree mills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point of this approach would be is its simplicity and resistance to gaming. Unlike entrance examinations that can be manipulated through coaching, this system measures actual learning outcomes. Colleges cannot simply teach to the test because the syllabus is already their prescribed curriculum. They would be forced to genuinely improve their teaching quality to ensure their graduates can demonstrate basic competency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Implementation would face predictable resistance—particularly from the thousands of substandard institutions that would face closure. However, the economic logic is compelling. Why should society continue subsidizing institutions that provide negative value? The short-term disruption of closing ineffective colleges would be vastly outweighed by the long-term benefits of concentrating resources on institutions that actually educate their students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This system would also solve the information asymmetry problem plaguing students and employers. Prospective students could evaluate colleges based on their graduates&apos; competency scores, while employers would have reliable indicators of actual capability rather than meaningless degree certificates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;2. Implementation and Broader Implications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The universal competency assessment model represents more than educational reform—it&apos;s a mechanism for restoring genuine meritocracy to Indian society. By making institutional performance transparent and consequential, this system would naturally concentrate educational resources on effective institutions while eliminating the parasitic elements that currently drain societal resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IT may be rightfully argued that closing thousands of colleges would create unemployment and social disruption. However, this perspective misses the crucial point: these institutions already fail to provide meaningful education or employment outcomes. Their closure would eliminate the elaborate fiction that wastes four years of students&apos; lives and their families&apos; resources while producing graduates unfit for productive employment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The would logically also create powerful market incentives for innovation in education delivery. Institutions facing closure would be motivated to experiment with new teaching methods, hire competent faculty, and develop genuine expertise in their fields. The competitive pressure would drive educational innovation in ways that regulatory mandates have consistently failed to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, this approach aligns with broader economic necessities. As global competition intensifies and artificial intelligence automates routine tasks, India desperately needs engineers capable of genuine innovation and problem-solving. The current system produces exactly the opposite—graduates trained to memorize and regurgitate information without developing analytical capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The financial aspects deserve particular attention. Rather than continuing to subsidize thousands of worthless institutions, society could redirect resources toward fewer, higher-quality colleges that demonstrate actual educational outcomes. This concentration of resources would enable these institutions to compete globally rather than merely existing as local degree mills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Conclusion: The Choice Before Us&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We face a stark choice between comfortable delusion and uncomfortable truth. We can continue maintaining illusions about our educational achievements while our competitive position erodes, or we can confront the reality that we have constructed an elaborate system for manufacturing ignorance and begin the difficult work of reconstruction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The underlying economic forces are inexorable. India cannot indefinitely sustain educational institutions that consume resources while producing negative value. The question is not whether change will come, but whether we will initiate it proactively or have it imposed upon us through competitive failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The educated-yet-ignorant graduate represents more than a product of our broken system—they embody our society&apos;s choice of credentials over competence, appearance over substance, and comfortable delusions over difficult truths. Breaking free from this trap requires acknowledging that we have made fundamental errors in our approach to human capital development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only through such acknowledgment can we begin building educational institutions worthy of India&apos;s aspirations and equal to the challenges of global competition. The alternative is continued decline disguised as progress, until external forces compel the reckoning we lack the courage to initiate ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><h:img src="/newBlog/_astro/cover.P9-NIKh0.jpeg"/><enclosure url="/newBlog/_astro/cover.P9-NIKh0.jpeg"/></item></channel></rss>